Guide to the Frederick Kelly Photograph Collection 1959-1976 (bulk 1961-1966) PR 246
New York University Libraries, Publisher
Frederick Kelly Photograph Collection 1959-1976 (bulk 1961-1966)
PR 246
1.5 lin. ft., 2 boxes
New-York Historical Society
Kelly, Frederick
250 black and white photographs, primarily taken of buildings and street life in New York City.
Provenance
Gift of Rena Kelly, 2004.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Frederick Kelly (1905-1999) lived in Baltimore, MD. He worked as a librarian at the Peabody Institute, until enrolling at Johns Hopkins University. He then taught English and industrial arts, and later served as the principal at Highwood School, a Baltimore public school, until 1975. Kelly's interests included photography, and he enjoyed traveling to New York City in his later years to photograph the vibrant city's buildings and people.
Scope and Content Note
The Frederick Kelly Photograph Collection spans the period from 1959-1976 and contains 250 black and white silver gelatin photographs, primarily taken in New York City. Photographs are grouped by geographical location, as indicated on the verso by Kelly, or by subject if exact location is not known. Kelly fastidiously documented most of the photographs on their verso with a date, title, type of camera used, and shutter speed and light information.
Kelly appears to have been interested in the myriad different characters that mark the fabric of urban life. In addition to people going to and from work and shopping, his photographs pay attention to homeless people, nuns, newsstands and street peddlers, street preachers, street musicians, and parades. Two female Macy's employees are shown on strike, walking with sandwich boards printed with their complaints. People of all ages lounge on benches, read newspapers, feed pigeons, window shop, chat, hurry across the street, and relax in parks.
Most of the photographs of people are candid; the subjects do not appear to have known their picture was being taken. A few photographs taken inside subway cars are the prime example of this; the passengers are unaware of the camera, and are captured sleeping, crocheting, and lost in thought among the crowds. In general, this quality lends these photographs a documentary air, and allows the views of the city to appear lived in and fresh.
The majority of the images were taken in Washington Square Park and Central Park, where Kelly, in his mid-to-late-60s when these photographs were taken, documented the colorful gatherings of young people. Photographs of Washington Square mainly involve young people playing music - on the guitar, banjo, and drums - singing, and relaxing together. One image of musicians is titled "Beat Generation." The photographs show both white and African American musicians and crowd members. One photograph shows several women students studying together on the grass. Other views of Greenwich Village include stores along Bleecker Street, West 4th Street, and an art studio on MacDougal Street.
The photographs of Central Park were mostly taken on two weekends in January and March of 1967. Crowds of young people play music, dance, ride bicycles, buy balloons, and visit the zoo. Several of the March 26 photos are titled "be-in." Horse-drawn tourist carriages are also shown driving in the park and down Fifth Avenue.
In addition to people, Kelly paid attention to the architecture of the city. Some of his views of buildings are decidedly artistic, some dead-on straight shots, and some also designed to show how buildings are experienced and used by city dwellers. Exteriors of buildings shown include the Empire State Building, St. Bartholomew's Church, the post office on Eighth Avenue, and the First National City bank building. Photographs of building interiors show Grand Central Station, Pennsylvania Station, and mannequins posed inside stores, including Lord & Taylor. Restaurants pictured are mostly cafes, some outdoor, and include Astor Cafeteria, Topp's, Shelley's Coffee Shop, the Waldorf Cafeteria, and Bidford's.
A few photographs of other cities include views of Philadelphia, PA, Norfolk, VA, and Washington, D.C. (including views of the Kennedy Center, the Watergate Hotel, and a 1961 Peace Concert on the Mall.)
Access Points
Subject Names:
Kelly, Frederick, 1905-1999
Subject Topics:
Street life -- New York (State) -- New York; Street vendors -- New York (State) -- New York; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Restaurants -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Office buildings -- New York (State).
Subject Places:
New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Chinatown (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Times Square (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Washington Square (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Fifth Avenue (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Central Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works
Document Types:
Gelatin silver prints; Cityscapes
Container List
  Photographs are arranged alphabetically by location, and thereunder by subject.
  - Battery Park (7 images), 1961 Nov.-1962 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bryant Park (6 images), 1961 Aug.-1963 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Central Park (33 images), 1967 Jan.-Mar; undated (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Chinatown (2 images), 1967 Aug; undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coney Island and Aquarium (5 images), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fifth Avenue (6 images), 1959 Jun.-1967 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street (5 images), 1961 Apr.-1963 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Greeley Square (7 images), 1961 Apr.-1967 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Greenwich Village (7 images), 1961 Apr.-1962 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Herald Square and 34th Street (4 images), 1961 Apr.-1962 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Metropolitan Museum (7 images), 1961 Aug.-1963 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Times Square (6 images), 1961 Apr.-1963 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Washington Square (Musicians and Singers), 1960 Apr.-1967 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - Washington Square (People and Washington Arch), 1960 Apr.-1967 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Views of lower Manhattan from Brooklyn (5 images), 1961 Aug.-1962 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Views of Manhattan taken from the top of the Empire State Building (4 images), 1959 Apr.-1961 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Views of Manhattan taken from the top of [a building in] Rockefeller Center (8 images), 1961 Nov.-1968 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Boats (3 images), 1959 Jun.-1967 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Building Exteriors (4 images), 1962 Apr. 19-23 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Building Interiors (9 images), 1961 Apr.-1962 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Restaurants (7 images), 1961 Apr.-1962 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Statuary (8 images), 1960 Apr.-1962 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Street Characters (16 images), 1960 May-1966 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Street Scenes (22 images), 1961 Apr.-1967 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Subway passengers (4 images), 1961 Apr.-1962 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous (6 items), 1962 Aug.; undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Other Cities (7 images), 1961 Oct.-1976 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 36)